Paul Muldoon papers, 1939-2010
Emory University
Paul Muldoon papers, 1939-2010
Muldoon, Paul.
Manuscript Collection No. 784
53.25 linear ft. (112 boxes) and 175 oversized papers (OP)
Papers of Irish poet Paul Muldoon, including correspondence, writings by Muldoon and others, printed material, business and personal papers, photographs and audiovisual material.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1996, with subsequent additions.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.1, Alphabetical Correspondence, some files are closed without the written permission of Paul Muldoon. Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers. Letters by Gerard Quinn are closed until Quinn's death.
Biographical Note
Paul Muldoon was born in County Armagh in 1951. He attended Queen's University in Belfast where he studied English literature under Seamus Heaney. In 1973, the year he graduated from Queen's, Faber and Faber published his first collection of poems. From 1973 to 1986 he worked as a radio and television producer for BBC Northern Ireland. He moved to the United States in 1987 and has held various university teaching posts. He currently lives in New Jersey and is the Howard G. B. Clark '21 Professor at Princeton University and Chair of the Peter B. Lewis Center for the Arts. Muldoon is married to novelist Jean Hanff Korelitz, with whom he has two children.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of the papers of Irish poet Paul Muldoon from 1939-2010, including correspondence, writings by Muldoon and others, printed material, business and personal papers, photographs and audiovisual material. The papers document Muldoon's creative work since the 1960s, including poetry, television and radio scripts for the BBC, drama and music. Correspondence in the collection consists primarily of letters to Muldoon from others, with only a few copies of letters written by Muldoon. The correspondence documents Muldoon's relationships with other Irish poets such as Ciaran Carson, Seamus Heaney, Michael Longley and Derek Mahon. Writings by Muldoon include drafts, proofs and other materials relating to his work as a poet, translator, and lyricist, as well as various types of prose writing. Writings by others include works by other Irish poets, interviews with Muldoon, and essays and theses about Muldoon's work.
Printed material consists of published writings by and about Muldoon, published writings by other authors, as well as some collected publications. Promotional material includes posters, flyers, brochures and other printed material publicizing and promoting Muldoon's work, poetry readings and other appearances. Business and personal papers consist primarily of publishing contracts, but also contain materials such as Muldoon's curriculum vitae, travel itineraries, appointment books and royalty statements. Photographs include portraits and snapshots of Muldoon, along with family members, friends and colleagues. Finally, the audiovisual material in the collection consists of recordings of performances of Muldoon's work, and a small number of interviews with Muldoon and reviews of Muldoon's poetry.
Arrangement Note
Organized into eight series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Writings by Paul Muldoon, (3) Writings by others, (4) Printed material, (5) Promotional materials, readings, and appearances, (6) Business and personal papers, (7) Photographs, and (8) Audiovisual material.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Carson, Ciaran, 1948-; Fallon, Peter, 1951-; Heaney, Seamus.; Longley, Michael, 1939-; McGuckian, Medbh, 1950-; Mahon, Derek, 1941-
Topical Terms
English literature--Irish authors--20th century.; English poetry--Irish authors.; Irish poetry--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.; Belfast Group.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scripts.; Sound recordings.; Translations.; Video recordings.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1962-2005, Series 1; Boxes 1-7, 47-65, and OP 1
  Scope and Content Note
  The series consists largely of incoming letters received by Muldoon between 1962 and 2005. The alphabetical correspondence is organized according to correspondent or subject and reflects Muldoon's original arrangement. Correspondents include Ciaran Carson, Peter Fallon, Seamus Heaney, Michael Longley, Medbh McGuckian, and Derek Mahon. A small number of letters by Paul Muldoon are also present. Along with conventional hand- or type-written correspondence, the series also includes extensive email correspondence, printed from Muldoon's computer. Correspondence of a more general nature may be found in the second subseries. Manuscript items in the correspondence series have been noted in the container list and cross references have been added.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into two subseries: (1.1) Alphabetical correspondence and (1.2) General correspondence.
  Restrictions on Access
  Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.1, Alphabetical Correspondence, some files are closed without the written permission of Paul Muldoon. Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers. Letters by Gerard Quinn are closed until Quinn's death.
  - Alphabetical correspondence, 1962-2005, Subseries 1.1; Boxes 1-5, 47-60, 111-112 and OP 1
    The subseries consists of correspondence sent and received between 1962 and 2005, arranged alphabetically by Muldoon by correspondent name or subject. Correspondents include Ciaran Carson, Peter Fallon, Seamus Heaney, Michael Longley, Medbh McGuckian, and Derek Mahon. Subjects include particular works and publications by Muldoon, as well as topics related to Ireland, English-language poetry and Muldoon's professional associations. Correspondence with composer Daron Hagen, as it largely concerns their collaborative works, is located in Subseries 2.2, Dramatic Works and Lyrics.
    Arranged in alphabetical order with restricted correspondence at the end.
    - 92nd Street Y and Unterberg Poetry Center, 1997-2001 (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - The Abbey Theatre, 1998-2000 (Box 47, Folder 2)
    - The Academy of American Poets, 1998 (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Allen, Michael, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Allen, Michael, 1998-2004 (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Allen, Michael, no date with two group sheets (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Allison Jonathan, 1996-2003 (Box 47, Folder 5)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 2000-2002 (Box 47, Folder 6)
    - American Ireland Fund Literary Award, 2004 (Box 47, Folder 7)
    - American Literary Translators Association, 2004 (Box 47, Folder 8)
    - American Scholar, 1997-2003 (Box 47, Folder 9)
    - Amichai, Yehuda, 2000 (Box 47, Folder 10)
    - Amis, Martin, 2001 (Box 47, Folder 11)
    - Antaeus [See Subseries 1.1: Ecco Press] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Aosdána, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aosdána, printed materials, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A.P. Watt, Ltd., 1996 (Box 47, Folder 12)
    - Armitage, Simon, 1995-2005 (Box 47, Folder 13)
    - The Arvon Foundation, 2004 (Box 47, Folder 14)
    - Asekoff, Louis, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Asekoff, Louis, 1997-2000 (Box 47, Folder 15)
    - Ashbery, John, 1998 (Box 47, Folder 16)
    - Auster, Paul, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Bangle, 1998 (Box 47, Folder 17)
    - Banks, Russell, 1995-1997 (Box 47, Folder 18)
    - Banlin, Nicola, 2000 (Box 47, Folder 19)
    - Bardwell, Leland, 2002, with uncorrected typescript of poem in tribute to Bardwell by Muldoon (Box 47, Folder 20)
    - Barfield, Brian, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Barfield, Brian, 2002 (Box 47, Folder 21)
    - Barnes, Julian, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bateson Memorial Lecture, University of Oxford, 1996-1998 (Box 47, Folder 22)
    - Batten, Guinn, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Batten, Guinn, 1998-2002 (Box 47, Folder 23)
    - Bender, Matthew, 1999-2000 [regarding proposed opera adaptation of The Last of the Mohicans] (Box 47, Folder 24)
    - Benfey, Christopher, no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Between the Lines, 1999-2002 (Box 47, Folder 25)
    - The Birds, 1995-2004 (Box 47, Folder 26)
    - Blackstaff Press, 2001 (Box 47, Folder 27)
    - Boland, Eavan, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bolger, Dermot, no date (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Book of Beasts, 1996-1998 (Box 47, Folder 28)
    - Borodale, Sean, 2004 (Box 47, Folder 29)
    - Brainerd, Stuart, 1997 (Box 47, Folder 30)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1995-2004 (Box 47, Folder 31)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation, no date (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, 1996-2003 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Brown, Rachel, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Byrne, Mairead, 2002-2004 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Carey, John, 1999 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Carr, Marina, 1996-1997 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - Carson, Ciaran, 1973-1988 with "Sleeping Together," carbon typescript [See also Subseries 1.1: Tess Gallagher and George Newson] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Carson, Ciaran, 1993 with photocopied typescript of First Language (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Carson, Ciaran, 1996-2002, with typescript of The Twelfth of Never and translation of Canto XXI of Dante's Inferno (Box 48, Folder 5)
    - Carson, Ciaran, 2003-2005 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - Carson, Ciaran, no date (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carter, Catherine, 1996-2002 (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - Cartmill, Deirdre, 2002, with typescript of four poems by Cartmill (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - Christo and Jeanne-Claude, March 1997 (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - Clampitt, Amy, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Clark, Heather, 2003, with typescript of dissertation chapter about Northern Ireland poets (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - Cliff, Brian, 1998-2004, with article typescript, "Poetry 'on the cusp': The manuscripts for Paul Muldoon's '7, Middagh Street'" (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Clifton, Harry, 1998 (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Cohen, Leonard, 2003-2004 (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - Collins, Diane, 2002 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - Columbia University, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Cone, Edward, 1998 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - Cone, Edward and George Pitcher, 1973-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Conner, Lester, 1982-1994, with 14 photographs of Muldoon in Pennsylvania, April 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Conner, Lester, no date, with essay about Samuel; Hynes (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - Conover, Roger, 1999 (Box 48, Folder 17)
    - Cope, Wendy, 1997-2002 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - Corcoran, Neil, 2000-2004 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - County Armagh (Northern Ireland), 1999-2005 (Box 48, Folder 20)
    - Cowdy, Belinda [See Subseries 1.1: Philip Haas] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Craobh Rua Books, 2002 (Box 48, Folder 21)
    - Cyrano de Bergerac, 1998 [translation by Paul Muldoon of Rostand's play, for the Abbey Theatre, Dublin] (Box 48, Folder 22)
    - Daisey, Mike, 2003-2004 (Box 48, Folder 23)
    - d'Amboise, Jacques, 2002-2003 (Box 48, Folder 24)
    - Davitt, Michael, 1982-1987, with typescripts of "Elena," "August," "Prayer 105," Disillusion Street," and "To Pound, From God" [See also Subseries 2.3, Translations] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Davitt, Michael, 2002 (Box 48, Folder 25)
    - Day-Lewis, Cecil, 2001-2004 (Box 48, Folder 26)
    - Deane, Seamus, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Deane, Seamus, 2003 (Box 48, Folder 27)
    - Delaney, Diarmuid, no date (Box 48, Folder 28)
    - Delantey, Greg, 1998-2002, with a printed keepsake poem by Delantey (Box 48, Folder 29)
    - DeLillo, Don, 2002-2003 (Box 48, Folder 30)
    - Devlin, Anne, 1996-1997 (Box 48, Folder 31)
    - Diaz, Junot, no date (Box 48, Folder 32)
    - Dingle, County Kerry (Northern Ireland), 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Dodge Poetry Festival, 2004-2005 (Box 48, Folder 33)
    - Donoghue, Denis, 2003-2004 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Donoghue, Denis, no date (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Drabble, Margaret, 1998 (Box 49, Folder 2)
    - The Drowned Blackbird, 2001 [translations by Paul Muldoon, published by the Gallery Press] (Box 49, Folder 3)
    - Duffy, Carol Ann, 1999-2003 (Box 49, Folder 4)
    - Duffy, Rita, 2003-2005 (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - Dufour Editions, Inc., 1997 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - Dunbar, Ann, 2001 (Box 49, Folder 7)
    - Dunn, Douglas, 1973-1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Dunn, Stephen, 1996 (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Durcan, Paul, 1976-1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Durcan, Paul, no date (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Ecco Press, 1986-1994 [See also Subseries 1.1: Wake Forest University Press] (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Ecco Press, 1998-2001 (Box 49, Folder 10)
    - Elliott, Judith, 2000-2001 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - The End of the Poem, book of lectures delivered by Muldoon as Oxford Professor of Poetry, 1999-2004 (Box 49, Folder 12)
    - Evans, Matthew, 2001 (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - European Prize for Poetry, 2004 (Box 49, Folder 14)
    - Faber and Faber, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Faber and Faber, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Faber and Faber, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Faber and Faber, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Faber and Faber, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Faber and Faber, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Faber and Faber, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Faber and Faber, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Faber and Faber, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Faber and Faber, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Faber and Faber, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Faber and Faber, 1995-2004 (Box 49, Folder 15)
    - Faber and Faber, no date (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Fagles, Robert, 1997-2004, with a translation by Fagles of lines 628-804 of Virgil's Aeneid (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Fallon, Peter [See Subseries 1.1: Gallery Press] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1989-1991 [See also Subseries 1.1: Jonathan Galassi] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Farrar, Strauss and Giroux, 1995-1999 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    - Farrar, Strauss and Giroux, Faber and Faber acquisition, 1998 (Box 49, Folder 18)
    - Farrar, Straus and Giroux, no date (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Feaver, Jane, no date (Box 49, Folder 19)
    - Fenton, James, 1999-2004 (Box 49, Folder 20)
    - Ferris, Kathleen, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Field Day Theatre Company [See Subseries 1.1: Brian Friel] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Fitzgerald, Fleur, 2001-2002 (Box 49, Folder 21)
    - Flint, Peter, 2004 (Box 49, Folder 22)
    - Flying Fox [See Subseries 1.1: David Hammond] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Foer, Jonathan Safran, 2002-2004 (Box 49, Folder 23)
    - Forché, Carolyn, 2001 (Box 49, Folder 24)
    - Ford, Richard, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ford, Richard, 1997-2001 (Box 49, Folder 25)
    - Foster, Richard, 1997-2001 (Box 49, Folder 26)
    - Foster, Roy, 1997-2004 (Box 49, Folder 27)
    - Fountains of Wayne, 2004 (Box 49, Folder 28)
    - Friel, Brian, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Friel, Brian, 1999 (Box 49, Folder 29)
    - Galassi, Jonathan, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Galassi, Jonathan, 2002 (Box 49, Folder 30)
    - Gallagher, Tess, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Gallery Press, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Gallery Press, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Gallery Press, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Gallery Press, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Gallery Press, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Gallery Press, 1995-2004 (Box 49, Folder 31)
    - Gallery Press, Christmas Cards, 1998-2004, featuring poems by Muldoon (Box 49, Folder 32)
    - Gallery Press, no date (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Gardini, Nicola, 1998-2001 (Box 49, Folder 33)
    - Gering, August, 1999-2002 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Goodby, John, 2001 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Greenlaw, Lavinia, 2002-2003 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Grennan, Eamon, 1984-1994 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Grennan, Eamon, 1998-2001 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Greytak, Sharon, 1996 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Griggstown Bridge, 2002 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Gritsman, Andrey, 2004, with typescript of "Belfast," by Gritsman (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Groarke, Vona, 1998-2000 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Groucho Club, 1995-2002 (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Gunn, Thom, 1998 (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Haas, Philip and Belinda Cowdy,1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Haas, Robert, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Hacker, Marilyn, no date (Box 50, Folder 11)
    - Hadan, Samuel, 2003 (Box 50, Folder 12)
    - Hagen, Daron [See Subseries 2.2, Dramatic Works and Lyrics] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Hall, Donald, 2000 (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Hammond, David, 1990, with photographs of Muldoon (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hammond, David, 1999-2001 (Box 50, Folder 14)
    - The Handsome Family, 2004 (Box 50, Folder 15)
    - Hardie, Kerry, no date (Box 50, Folder 16)
    - Harsent, David, 1996-2003 (Box 50, Folder 17)
    - Hassett, Joseph, 2002-2005 (Box 50, Folder 18)
    - Hawthorne, Denys, 1984-1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Hawthorne, Denys, 1995-2004 (Box 50, Folder 19)
    - Hay, 1997-2000 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Heffernan, Margaret, no date (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Hejinian, Lyn, 2004 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Healy, Dermot, no date (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Heaney, Seamus [See Subseries 1.1: Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Heaney, Seamus, correspondence from Paul Muldoon to Seamus Heaney, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Heaney, Seamus, correspondence from Paul Muldoon to Seamus Heaney, 1995-1996 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Heaney, Seamus, correspondence from Paul Muldoon to Seamus Heaney, 1997-2004 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Hefferman, Margaret, 1986-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Henley, William Ernest, 2003 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Hertford College, University of Oxford, 1999-2004 (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Hicks, Jerry, 1996-1997 (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Hofmann, Michael, 2003-2004 (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Hollander, John, 2000 (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Holub, Miroslav, 1998 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Honest Ulsterman, 1969-1995 [See also Subseries 1.1: James Simmons] (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Honest Ulsterman, 1996-2000 (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - Honorary degrees, 2000-2004 [1 of 2] (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Honorary degrees, 2000-2004 [2 of 2] (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - An Horatian Ode, 2001 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Hughes, Frieda, 2001 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Hughes, John, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hughes, John, 1997-2002 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Hughes, Ted, 1983-1994 with photocopied manuscript of "Ode to the Organism" (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Hughes, Ted, 1995-2004 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - International IMPAC Dublin Literary Award, 1997-1998 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Irish Copyright Licensing Agency, 2001 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Irish Folk and Fairy Tales, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Japan, 1996-2000 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Jen, Gish, 2000 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Jenkins, Alan, 1982-1995 with photocopied typescripts of "The Quilt," and "Jellyfish" (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Jenkins, Alan, 2003 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Jenkins, Nicholas, 1986-1991 with photocopied typescript of poem attributed to W.H. Auden (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Jenkins, Niel, 1995-1999, with typescript review of The Annals of Chile by Jenkins (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Johnston, Jennifer, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Johnstone, Robert, no date [See also Subseries 1.1: Honest Ulsterman] (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Joseph, Lawrence, 1987-1995 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Keegan, Paul, 1999 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Kendall, Tim, 1994-1995 [See also Subseries 3.2: Theses and unpublished articles, essays, and interviews and Subseries 4.2: Writings by others.] (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Kendall, Tim, 1996-2005 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Kennelly, Brendan, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Kerry Slides, 1998-2001 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - Kiely, Ben, no date (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Kinnell, Galway, 2003 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Kinsella, John, 1999-2002, with typescript of "Drugs and Country Towns," poem by Kinsella dedicated to Muldoon (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Knox, Tony, 1995-2001 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - Koch, Kenneth, 1999-2002 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Krauss, Nicole, 2001, with typescript introduction by Krauss to a Muldoon poetry reading (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - Krementz, Jill, 1996 (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - Kushner, Tony, 1997 (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Laitman, Lori, 2003-2004, with musical settings by Laitman to various poems by Muldoon (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - Laine, Frankie, 1999-2002, with sheet music composed by Laine (Box 52, Folder 24)
    - Lea, Sydney, 2003 (Box 52, Folder 25)
    - Lehman, David, 1998 (Box 52, Folder 26)
    - Leithauser, Brad, 1998 (Box 52, Folder 27)
    - London Review of Books, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Longley, Edna, 1984-1994 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Longley, Michael 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Longley, Michael, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Longley, Michael, 1990, with photocopied typescript of Gorse Fires (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Longley, Michael, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Longley, Edna and Michael, 1996-2004 (Box 52, Folder 28)
    - Longley, Edna and Michael, no date (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Loyola Marymount University, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Lyons, Gilda, 1998, with musical score by Lyons (Box 52, Folder 29)
    - MacArthur, Marit, 2003-2004 (Box 52, Folder 30)
    - MacNeice, Louis, 1997-1998 (Box 52, Folder 31)
    - McAleese, Mary, 1999-2003 (Box 52, Folder 32)
    - McCauley, Roisin, 2004 (Box 52, Folder 33)
    - McBeath, Norman, 1998-2003, with photographs by McBeath for proposed poetry and photography book collaboration between McBeath and Muldoon (Box 52, Folder 34)
    - McCaffery, A.J., 1997 (Box 52, Folder 35)
    - McCall, Marina, 2002 (Box 52, Folder 36)
    - McCann, Colum, 2000 (Box 52, Folder 37)
    - McClatchy, J.D., 2000-2001 (Box 52, Folder 38)
    - McCloskey, Francis, 2000 (Box 52, Folder 39)
    - McCracken, Kathleen, 1983-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - McCracken, Kathleen, 2000 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - McCrum, Robert, 2002, with typescript poem by Muldoon about McCrum's wedding (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - McCurry, Jacqueline, 1997-2000 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - McDermott, Alicia, no date (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - McDiarmid, Lucy, 2002 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - McDiarmid, Niall, 1997 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - McDonald, Peter, 1996-2004 (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - McGahern, John, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - McGahern, John, 2001-2002 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - McGovern, Barry, 1996 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - McGuckian, Medbh, 1980-1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - McGuckian, Medbh, no date (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - McHugh, Heather, 1996-2003 (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - McKay, Mari, 1997-2004 (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - McKendrick, Jamie, 2000-2002 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - McKeown, Diarmuid, 2004 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - McLaverty, Michael, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - McPhee, John, 1998-2002 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Maddox, Brenda, 1999 (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - Magee, Donald, 1996, with Muldoon family genealogy (Box 53, Folder 16)
    - Maguire, Sarah, 1989-1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Mahon, Derek, 1977-1992, with page proof of Mahon's review of Quoof, and photocopied typescript of Mahon's review of The Faber Book of Contemporary Irish Poetry (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Mahon, Derek, no date, with typescript of "The Joycentenary Ode" and "Everything is Going to be Alright" (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Marcus, Greil, 2002-2004 (Box 53, Folder 17)
    - Martin, Steve, 2002-2005 (Box 53, Folder 18)
    - Mason, Patrick, 2004 (Box 53, Folder 19)
    - Mathes, Rob, 2002-2004, with email collaboration on song lyrics [See also Subseries 2.2, Dramatic Works and Lyrics] (Box 53, Folder 20)
    - Matthews, Steven, circa 1998 (Box 53, Folder 21)
    - Maxwell, Glyn, 2002-2003 (Box 53, Folder 22)
    - Medley for Morin Khur, sonnet sequence published by Enitharmon Press, 2003-2004 (Box 53, Folder 23)